<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A perfite platforme of a hoppe garden and necessarie instructions for the making and mayntenaunce thereof, with notes and rules for reformation of all abuses, commonly practised therein, very necessary and expedient for all men to haue, which in any wise haue to doe with hops. Made by Reynolde Scot.</title>
            <author>Scot, Reginald, 1538?-1599.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1574</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 95 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 36 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A11622</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 21865</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S103209</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99838966</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99838966</idno>
            <idno type="VID">3359</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A11622)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 3359)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1219:06)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A perfite platforme of a hoppe garden and necessarie instructions for the making and mayntenaunce thereof, with notes and rules for reformation of all abuses, commonly practised therein, very necessary and expedient for all men to haue, which in any wise haue to doe with hops. Made by Reynolde Scot.</title>
                  <author>Scot, Reginald, 1538?-1599.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[14], 55 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Henrie Denham, dwelling in Pater noster Rovve, at the signe of the Starre,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1574. Cum priuilegio ad imprimendum solum.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Some print show-through.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Hops --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:3359:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:3359:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A Perfite platforme of a Hoppe Garden, and neceſſarie Inſtructions for the making and mayntenaunce thereof, with notes and rules for reformation of all abuſes, commonly practiſed therein, very neceſſary and expedient for all men to haue, which in any wiſe haue to doe with Hops.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Made by Reynolde Scot.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Prouer. 11.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <l>Whoſo laboureth after goodneſſe, findeth his deſire.</l>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Sap. 7.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <l>Wiſedome is nymbler than all nymble things:</l>
               <l>She goeth through and attayneth to all things.</l>
            </q>
            <p>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> Imprinted at London by Henrie <hi>Denham, dwelling in Pater noster</hi> Rovve, at the Signe of the Starre. 1574. <hi>Cum priuilegio ad imprimendum ſolum.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:3359:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:3359:2"/>
            <head>¶To the Right worſhipfull <hi>May<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster Willyam Louelace, Eſquire, Sergeaunt at the Lawe.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Yr, conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rynge the whole courſe of youre lyfe, howe it alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gither tendeth to the neceſsitie, to the profyte, and to the commendati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of your Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie, namely, in ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecution of Iuſtice, in dyrection of Counſell, and in mayntenance of Hoſpitalitie: waying alſo the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition of your nature, howe it rather inclyneth to procure commodities, that make to the encreaſe of your expences, than to deuyſe argument of priuate profite, to the qualifying of your charges, and laſt of all, acknowledging my ſelfe bounde vnto you in many dutyes, (as being laden vnder the burthen of your benefites) I thought good to entertayne your curteſie with ſome thankfull deuyſe, which myght neyther interrupt theſe your proceedings, nor em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>payre your eſtimation, nor yet obſcure the liberall diſpoſition of your mynde, and that none other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe,
<pb facs="tcp:3359:3"/> but by waye of requeſt, deſiring you, to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companye theſe your affections, with a matter of profite, or rather vvith a poynt of good Husbandrie, (in apparance baſe and tedious, but in vſe neceſſarie and commodious, and in effect pleaſant and profita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble) (that is to ſaye) to looke downe into the bow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>els of your grounde, and to ſeeke about your houſe at Bedderſden, (which I ſee you deſire to garniſhe with many coſtly commodities) for a conuenient plot to be applyed to a Hoppe garden, to the furthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance and accompliſhing whereof, I promyſe and aſſure you, the labour of my handes, the aſsiſtance of mine aduyſe, and the effect of myne experience: And herein I rather craue pardon for my preſent boldeneſſe, than thankes for my promiſe paſt, or prayſe for my paynes to come, as hauing more cauſe to ingraue your benefites in ſtone, and to proclayme them in the Market place, than to print them in the duſt, or to rake them vp in a Hoppe hyll, but beeing deſirous to proſecute the affection I beare vnto you, to the vttermoſt of my power, I ſet my good will in ſteade of better abilitie, in this ſort, to meete with your friendlyneſſe towardes me, and if it ſhall pleaſe you, being of ſuch condicion and reputation (not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding the indignitie of the matter) to allowe of this motion, you ſhall thereby eſpecially warrant the good opinion which is generallye conceyued of your good nature, increaſe the meaſure of your curteſie towardes me, and finally make many other beholding vnto you, for whoſe ſake I ſhall publiſhe a note for their profite and commoditie, and though
<pb facs="tcp:3359:3"/> it be vnto you a matter of ſmall importaunce, for that <hi>he which is full, abhorreth the Hony combe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Prouer. 27.</note> yet in aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much as I preſent herein a mynde that wiſheth well vnto you, appeaching my diſabilitie, and giuing in euidence agaynſt my ſloth, producing as witneſſe hereof, a hande ready to doe, a penne to wryte, and a tongue to ſpeake well of you, I hope the well mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of my deuice ſhall bee by you accepted, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though the merite of my deede may iuſtly bee con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned, my writings wanting forme, my wyſhes effect: and be it alſo knowne to all men by theſe pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentes, that your acceptance hereof ſhall not bee in any wyſe preiudiciall vnto you, for I delyuer it as an Obligation, wherein I acknowledge my ſelfe to ſtande further bounde vnto you, without that, that I meane to receyue your courteſie herein, as a releaſe of my further duties, which I owe vnto you. And although my matter be baſe, my deuyce ſimple, and my ſtyle homely, eſpecially for the contentacion of a delicate eare, yet I truſt it ſhall be <hi>gnitum opus agricolis,</hi> vnto whoſe capacities I haue directed the tenour hereof, not bumbaſting the ſame with the figures and flovvers of eloquence, to the glorye of my pen, or to the obſcuring of this miſterie, which although it ſhall ſeeme plauſible vnto ſome (through the exce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding profite leuied thereby.) Truely Sir, myne one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye meaning is hereby to gratifie you, and to ſatisfie the neceſsitie of my Countrie, and not to giue the reynes to inſatiable <hi>Heraclitus,</hi> or to niggardlye <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſtides,</hi> which couet to quench their thirſt with the licour (or rather the lucre) of flowing gaynes, nor
<pb facs="tcp:3359:4"/> to fill the paunche of Epicure, nor yet to paumper him in his eaſe and ydleneſſe, neyther to ballace the belly of Bacchus, or to lull or rocke Aeſchilus in hys drowſineſſe, which ſort of people are greedy to taſte of the marrowe of gaynes, and loth to breake the bone of labour, which is the myddle and both endes of this experience, and therefore this ſpeciall note I will here ſet downe for a generall rule. The coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous man that lyeth in wayte to ſpare his halfepe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nye, the ſluggarde that ſleepeth awaye oportunitie, and the vnskilfull that refuſeth to learne the ryght order; maye happily relleſſe the bitterneſſe of the Hoppe, but ſhall neuer ſauour the ſweeteneſſe ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, and yet if Hoppes woulde be had with wyſhes, or if commodities might bee bought vvith deſire, vvho vvoulde be better prouided than theſe men, name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye theſe, that make their prouiſion lying in their beddes, or ſitting by the fire, and in the ende buye a great Kyte in ſteade of a little Larke, vvhoſe mindes voyde of vvyſedome, make their Purſes manye ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes voyde of mony, and their doyngs voyde of ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect: for the eſchuing of all ſuch inconueniences, as in this matter may happen, I meane if it ſhall ſeeme good vnto you, to publiſhe this Pamphlet, vvherein if any thing haue eſcaped conſideration, I ſubmit the ſame to the correction of any other man better prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyſed herein than I am: in the meane time I heartily deſire you to allovve of my motion, and to ſatiſfie my requeſt.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Reynolde Scot.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:3359:4"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Lthoughe <hi>Salomon</hi> wyſheth vs not to <hi>take ouermuch paines to be riche,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Prou. 23.</note> ſignifying vnto vs thereby, that <hi>the man that ſo doth,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Prou. 28.</note> 
               <hi>can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not bee vnguiltie,</hi> and though he ſaye further, that <hi>greedye traueyle dooth nothing herein preuayle,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Prouer. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> in as much as <hi>it is the bleſsing of the Lorde that maketh men riche,</hi> and albeit,<note place="margin">Ibidem.</note> he alſo ſaye in apparance to the contentacion of the Idle, that <hi>one hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full is better with reſt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſi. 4.</note> 
               <hi>than both handes full with labour and traueyle.</hi> Yet the ſame <hi>Salomon</hi> alſo ſayeth, that <hi>the ſlothfull bodie that will not go to the Plough in Winter for colde, ſhall begge in the Sommer for neede,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Prou. 20.</note> giuing vs to vnderſtande thereby, that <hi>a ſimple man that worketh,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Prou. 12.</note> 
               <hi>is in better caſe than a gorgious man that wanteth,</hi> by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe <hi>the diligent hande ſhall proceede in authoritie,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Prou. 13.</note> 
               <hi>whyle the Idle perſon ſhall remayne vnder tribute.</hi> Hee ſayeth alſo in deſpyte of Idleneſſe, that,<note place="margin">Prou. 10.</note> 
               <hi>the ſlothfull is brother to the waſter,</hi> and in contempt of ſloth, that, <hi>the ſluggarde ſhall go in a ragged coate,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſi. 10.</note> ſhewing vs howe <hi>through ſloth our bankes fall downe,</hi> and howe <hi>through the Idleneſſe of our handes, it rayneth into our houſes.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ibidem.</note> Finally, he ſayeth to the comfort of the poore, that <hi>they which be diligent ſhall ſtande before Kinges,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Prou. 22.</note> 
               <hi>and not in common places,</hi> and therefore. <hi>Salomon</hi> meant not to impeach a paynefull hande, but to controule a couetous mynde, in witneſſe whereof he ſendeth the Idle ſluggard <hi>that ſleepeth at home, to the buſie Emmet that worketh abroade,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Prou. 6.</note> and <hi>the ſturdie runnagate that hath none aby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding,</hi> to the ſéeble <hi>Conye that buyldeth among the rocks,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Prou. 30.</note>
               <pb facs="tcp:3359:5"/> euen to be taught by thoſe ſielye wormes to correct them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, and thus is the couetous man condemned, bicauſe he ſetteth good conſcience behinde his gréedie deſires, and placeth his priuate profite before common humanitie, to erect vnto himſelfe and his poſteritie, a kingdome of va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie and ydleneſſe. The ſlothfull man is confounded, bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he abuſeth the tyme lent vnto him, as though he onely among all the Creatures of God, had a ſpeciall priuiledge to be ydle and careleſſe: and therefore I am bolde to commende this worke vnto you, euen ſo farre forth as the right vſe and purpoſe thereof deſerueth (that is to ſaye) as a recompence to the labourer, as a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moditie to the houſekéeper, as a comfort to the poore, and as a benefite to the Countrie or Common wealth, adding thus much herevnto, that there cannot lightly be employed grounde to more profitable vſe, nor labour to more certayne gaynes: howbeit, with this note, that no myſterie is ſo perfect, no floure ſo ſwéete, no Scripture ſo holy, but by abuſe a corrupt body, according to his ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nomous nature, may drawe poyſon out of the ſame, and therefore blame not this poore trade for that it maketh men riche in yéelding double profite, neyther reprooue me bicauſe by theſe preſents I giue notice therof, in pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhing this order, but condemne the man, or rather the mynde, that wreſteth it to ſerue his miſerable affection, or couetous humour. Truely it gréeueth me daylye to ſée time yll ſpent, labour loſt, coſt caſt awaye, much good grounde naughtily applyed, and many good men ſhame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully abuſed, through ignorance and ignorant workemen that vndertake to deale herin; I ſée almoſt euery man ſet his hand to work, or his head to deuiſe hervpon. Finally, I ſée the Flemmings enuie our practiſe herein, who alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gither tende their owne profite, ſéeking to impownde vs in the ignoraunce of our commodities, to cramme vs with the wares and fruites of their Countrie, and to doe anye thing that might put impediment to this purpoſe,
<pb facs="tcp:3359:5"/> dazeling vs with the diſcommendation of our ſoyle, ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcuring and falſifying the order of this myſterie, ſending vs into Flaunders as farre as Poppering, for that which we may finde at home in our owne backſides. But it were better (in my iudgement) to vnlearne that whych is conceyued amiſſe, and to vndoe that which is vnprofi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tably done, than to procéede with loſſe, and to ende with deriſion, it were better alſo that Straungers ſhoulde en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uye our proſperities, than our friendes ſhoulde pittie our pouerties, or that we our ſelues ſhoulde lament and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayle our owne neceſſities, procéeding from our negli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence in this behalfe. Nowe therefore let this ſuffyce to entreate you to conſider herevppon, and then let your owne conſideration preuayle to mooue you to take the worke in hande, and ſo are you made an arbitrer of your owne commodity, as being deſired to meaſure your char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges by your profite: I ſaye therefore to you that ſhall be hereby perſwaded to be dooing herin, giue eare to the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, giue diligence to the woorking, and doubtleſſe you ſhall giue credite and good report to the ſequele hereof. Howbeit, I for my part can better vſe my hande in doo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, than my penne in deſcrybing this myſterie. Neuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſſe, hoping hereby to ſtande my friendes and coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie in ſome profitable ſteade; I rather chooſe to incurre the daunger of deriſion in ſpeaking homelye, than the fault of ingratitude in ſaying nothing, the reſpect of dutie vanquiſhing in me the feare of yll report, mine ignorance crauing pardon, mine affection, good will, and let them that are ſo daungerous of their cunning go for mée wyth <hi>Tymon</hi> into the Deſert, there ſolitarilye to enioye their daintie wyſedome. And to ſaye the troth, to vſe eloquent ſchoole phraſes in a homely ruſtical matter, were to bring the Countrie people to a newe forme of hearing, wherin they ſhoulde be longer in learning to vnderſtande the cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rioſitie of the ſtyle, than the knowledge of the Arte, for ſuch menne (ſuch men I meane whoſe hope is in their
<pb facs="tcp:3359:6"/> handes) haue not bene brought vppe in a cloaſe ſtudie to diſcipher the Arte of Rhetoricke with their wittes, but haue bene trayned in the open fieldes to practyſe the Arte of Huſbandrie with their Lymmes, as being placed in the frontiers of pouertie, to beare the brunt of traueyle and labour, and therefore it ſuffyceth, if in a rude Caſke I exhibite wholeſome fruite, and write plainly to playne men of the Countrie, and yet <hi>Saepe etiam eſt holitor valde o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portuna locutus.</hi> In this ſort I ſhall teach I truſt without great error or tediouſneſſe, and you ſhall learne (I hope) without great payne or charges, the manner howe, the tyme when, and the place where to plant Hoppes wyth effect: God giue you encreaſe according to his holy will, and to your good deſire. In the meane time I deſire of the learned, pacience in reading, of the vnlearned, diligence in hearing, of the rich, ſome expences toward their great commoditie, of the poore, ſome payne for much profite, and of them all, good wyll for myne endeuour. Finallye, I hartily deſire you that when you haue once conformed your ſelfe to the right order, you procéede accordinglye, otherwiſe neyther of vs ſhall be any thing the neare, you of your purpoſe, nor I of my deſire, and if there be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayned herein any note of profitable inſtruction, applye the ſame to your owne commoditie. If the Lorde bleſſe your indeuour with encreaſe, yéelde vnto him (as vnto whome the ſame appertayneth) all prayſe and thankes there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Reynolde Scott.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="printer_to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:3359:6"/>
            <head>¶The Printer to the <hi>Reader.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>ORASM<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>CH, AS M. Scot could not be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent at the printing of this his Booke, whereby I might haue vſed his aduiſe in the correction of the ſame, and eſpeciallye of the Figures and Portratures contayned therein, whereof he deliuered vnto me ſuch notes as I being vnskilfull in the matter, could not ſo throughly conceyue, nor ſo perfect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly expreſse, as the expectation of him be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Author, or of you being the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, might be in all poyntes ſatisfied. J ſhall deſire you to let his abſence ſerue for mine excuſe in this behalfe, I alſo pray you to take ſomewhat the more pai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes in conferring the wordes with the fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gures, which will mutually giue lyght
<pb facs="tcp:3359:7"/> one to the other, and finallye will aſsist the vnderstanding of you the Reader, but chieflye of him that cannot reade at all, for whoſe ſake hee deuiſed and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cured theſe Figures to bee made, and howſoeuer the Paynter hath performed his office, or I my ſeruice herein, I am perſwaded that the Author hath perfite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye accompliſhed his dutie, and plainely deliuered vnto you the effect of that which he hath ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken in hande</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Farewell.</salute>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:3359:7"/>
            <head>¶The Table.</head>
            <list>
               <item>A Perfite Platforme of a Hoppe garden. fol. 1.</item>
               <item>Of vnapt and apt grounde for Hoppes. fol. 1</item>
               <item>Of the Scituation. fol. 3</item>
               <item>Of the quantitie. fol. 4</item>
               <item>A proportion of the charge and benefite of a Hoppe garden. fol. 4</item>
               <item>Of the preparation of a Hoppe garden. fol. 6</item>
               <item>The time to cut and ſet Hoppe Rootes. fol. 7</item>
               <item>Rules for the choyce and preparation of Rootes. fol. 7</item>
               <item>Of the good Hoppe. fol. 8</item>
               <item>Of the vnkindly Hoppe. fol. 8</item>
               <item>Of the wylde Hoppe. fol. 9</item>
               <item>Of ſetting of Hoppe rootes. fol. 9</item>
               <item>Abuſes and diſorders in ſetting. fol. 13</item>
               <item>Prouiſion agaynſt annoyaunce, and ſpoyle of your Garden. fol. 14</item>
               <item>¶Of Poales. fol. 14</item>
               <item>Of the erection of Poales. fol. 18</item>
               <item>Of Ramming of Poales. fol. 19</item>
               <item>Of Reparation of Poales. fol. 19</item>
               <item>Of the preſeruation of Poales. fol. 20</item>
               <item>¶Of tying of Hoppes to the Poales. fol. 22</item>
               <item>¶Of hylling and hylles. fol. 23</item>
               <item>Abuſes in hylling. fol. 27</item>
               <item>¶Of the gathering of Hoppes. fol. 29</item>
               <item>¶What there is to be done in vvinter herein. fol. 32</item>
               <item>¶The order for reforming your grounde. fol. 33</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:3359:8"/>
               <item>¶The order of cutting Hoppe rootes. fol. 33</item>
               <item>Of diuers mennes follyes. fol. 36</item>
               <item>Of diſorders and maintayners thereof. fol. 37</item>
               <item>¶Of an Oſte. fol. 38</item>
               <item>Of the ſeuerall Roumes for an Oſte. fol. 38</item>
               <item>Of the Furnace or Keele. fol. 39</item>
               <item>Of the bedde or vpper floore of the Oſte, vvhereon the Hoppes muſt be dryed. fol. 40</item>
               <item>The orderly drying of Hoppes. fol. 42</item>
               <item>Other maners of dryings not ſo good. fol. 45</item>
               <item>The very woorſt way of drying Hoppes. fol. 46</item>
               <item>Of not drying. fol. 47</item>
               <item>¶Of the packing of Hoppes. fol. 47</item>
               <item>¶The reformation of a Garden of vvylde Hops. fol. 49</item>
               <item>¶The reformation of a diſordered Garden. fol. 50</item>
               <item>¶Needeleſſe curioſities vſed by the vnskilfull. fol. 51</item>
               <item>The Epilogue. fol. 53</item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>Faultes eſcaped.</head>
            <p>In the .xix. Page, and the .xxij. lyne (that is to ſaye) in the firſt lyne of the tytle of Reparation of Poales, for, If anye of your Poales, reade, If any of the Poales, and in the next lyne ſaue one, for the broken Poale, reade the ſame broken Poale.</p>
            <p>In the .xxj. Page, and in the .xxiij. lyne, for ouerthwart, reade croſſe or thwart.</p>
            <p>In the .xxiiij. Page, and in the ſeconde lyne, and the firſt word, for ſythe, reade, ſnythe, and in the .xxj. lyne of the ſame Page, for appeare, reade, declare.</p>
            <p>In the .xxvj. Page, lyne .xxij. for long, reade, great. In the ſame Page, and in the next lyne, for longer, reade, greater.</p>
            <p>In the .xxix. Page, lyne. xxviij. for, here is inſtrument, reade, one inſtrument.</p>
            <p>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>d. for, as as, reade, as.</p>
            <p>In the .xxxiij. Page, lyne .xxiij. for, you muſt of neceſſitie, reade, you muſt nowe of neceſſitie.</p>
            <p>In the .xxxvj. Page, lyne. j. for the hyll, reade, and the hyll.</p>
            <p>In the .xxxix. Page, lyne .xxix. for, and not, reade, and of.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:3359:8"/>
            <head>¶A perfite Platforme of a <hi>Hoppe garden</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>T what time neceſſitie, or anye other good conſideration ſhall mooue you to deuyſe for a Hoppe garden, you are to conſider of theſe three thynges.</p>
            <p>Firſt, whether you haue, or can procure vnto your ſelfe, any grounde good for that purpoſe.</p>
            <p>Secondly, of the conuenient ſtanding therof.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, of the quantitie.</p>
            <p>And this I ſaye by the waye, if the grounde that you deale withall, be not your owne enheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taunce, procure vnto your ſelfe ſome certayne terme therein, leaſt another man reape the fruite of your traueyle and charge.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of apt and vnapt grounde for Hoppes.</head>
               <p>SOme holde at this daye (and Auncient wryters wytneſſe the ſame) that earth being ſalt and bitter of taſte,<note place="margin">Virgilius.</note> is neyther good, nor apt to be made good.</p>
               <p>It is alſo often written, and generally recey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, that ſuch earth as you ſhall ſee whyte and bare (that is to ſaye) wholy chalke, or all ſande lacking a mixture of perfyte earth,<note place="margin">Didymus.</note> or if it bee clayie, or ſo drie,<note place="margin">Plinius.</note> as thereby it ſhall gape or coane in the ſummer, is naught. &amp;c.</p>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:3359:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <p>It is further ſayde, that if you ſhall feele a clod (being diſſolued with water) to be very clammy, or cleauing like Waxe to your fyngers in knea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding it, the ſame to be profytable lande. &amp;c.</p>
               <p>I for my part relye not vpon other mens opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions, neyther meane to diſpute with anye man herein, I lyke not to make my mouth an arbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trer in this matter, mine eye maye be deceyued, and my feeling may erre in the precyſe diſtinction of good or bad lande, but mine experience hath neuer fayled in this thing (that is to ſaye) that a barren, a moorie or wette ſoyle (though it per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps doe content a wylde Hoppe) ſhall neuer pleaſe nor maintayne a good Hoppe.</p>
               <p>I will not ſay with <hi>Varro,</hi> that a good ground yeeldeth Walwoortes, nor with <hi>Columella,</hi> that where Crabbes or Sloes growe, there the grounde is riche. I can ſaye nothing of <hi>Floren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tines</hi> experience, in digging a hole, and fylling it vppe agayne, and by the ſwelling to iudge the ſtrength, or by the gaping to defyne the weake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe thereof, but I can ſay againe by ſure expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience, that a drie grounde, if it be riche, meoloe, and gentle, is the ſoyle that ſerueth beſt for this purpoſe, and ſuch a moulde muſt either be ſought out, or elſe by coſt and labour be prouoked.</p>
               <p>If it be a verye ſhallowe rocke (except you rayſe it with greete or good earth) you ſhall not ſet your Poales deepe, ſteddye, and faſt ynough, to withſtande the force of the winde.</p>
               <p>To redreſſe the inconuenience herof, you ſhall
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:3359:9" rendition="simple:additions"/> be taught in the tytle of Poales.</p>
               <p>A lyght moulde (though it be very rich) is not very apt for this purpoſe, for it is a receyued and a prooued rule, that the heauyeſt grounde wyll beare the moſt weyght of Hoppes, I ſaye, ſo as it be a grounde apt for this purpoſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of the Scituation.</head>
               <p>IT were good to place your Garden ſo as the Sunne maye haue free recourſe into it, eyther the whole daye, or the greateſt and warmeſt part thereof, ſo alſo as if maye bee armed againſt the violence and contagion of the Eaſternlye and Northernlye wynde, but this I woulde wiſhe to be conſidered rather in the ſitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation of the place, naturallye defended with a Northernly or Eaſternlye hill, than artificiallye be ſet and garded with trees. Howbeit, if you be driuen herevnto, prouide ſo (if you can) that your trees may ſtande aloofe, euen that the ſhadowe of them, reache not into your Garden, but in any wiſe that they droppe not vpon the hylles.</p>
               <p>It ſhoulde alſo be placed neare to your houſe, except you be able to warrant the fruite thereof from ſuch fyngers as put no difference betweene their owne and other mens goodes.</p>
               <p>Alſo your Garden being thus placed, there may be made thervnto the more ſpeedie and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuall recourſe, beſides that, that the Maiſters eye ſhall manye times withſtande and preuent
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:3359:10"/> the ſeruants negligence.</p>
               <p>Finally, by this meanes, it may be with moſt eaſe and leaſt charge holpen with dunge.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of the quantitie.</head>
               <p>THe quantitie of your Garden, muſt ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther bee meaſured by the proportion of your yerely expences of Hoppes in your houſe, or by the coſt you meane to beſtowe in the preparation and keeping thereof, or by the paynes and buſineſſe that you are diſpoſed, or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to employe vppon it, or elſe according to the profite and gaynes, that you meane to leuie and winne by it, which later conſideration plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth and flattereth much a couetous mannes conceyt, whoſe vaine or humor, (or rather vaine humor) is ſo reſiſted in the rules appertayning herevnto, as many times the greedineſſe of his deſire, is the ouerthrowe of his purpoſe, as ſhall hereafter appeare.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A proportion of the charge and benefite of a Hoppe garden.</head>
               <p>BVt to be reſolued in all theſe poyntes that conſcerne the quantitie of your Garden, you muſt make your account in this voyſe.</p>
               <p>One man may well keepe twoo thouſand hils, and yet reſerue his wynters labor for anye other purpoſe.</p>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:3359:10"/>
               <p>Vppon euery Acre you maye erect ſeauen, eyght, or nyne hundreth hylles, as hereafter ſhall be declared.</p>
               <p>Vpon euery hyll well ordered, you ſhall haue three poundes of Hoppes at the leaſt.</p>
               <p>Three poundes of theſe Hoppes will largely ſerue for the bruing of one quarter of Mault.</p>
               <p>One hundreth poundes of theſe Hoppes, are commonly woorth .xxvj. s. viij. d. So as one a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cre of grounde, and the thirde part of one mans labor, with ſmall coſt beſides, ſhall yeelde vnto him that ordereth the ſame well, fortye markes yearely, and that for euer.</p>
               <p>And here is to be noted, that grounde orderly vſed, doth not only yeelde the more, the greater, the harder, and the weyghtyer Hoppes, but alſo they ſhall goe further, they ſhall endure longer, they ſhall be holeſommer for the body, and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaunter of verdure or taſte, than ſuch as be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orderly handled.</p>
               <p>Theſe things conſidered, you may proceede to the making of your Gardeyn, wherein you are yet to haue counſell, for the laying out thereof, for the due ſeaſon and the right trade to cut and ſet Hoppe rootes, what choyſe you ſhall make of them, what charge you ſhall be at for them, you are yet alſo to learne the tyme, when, and the way how to prepare your grounde, and to make it able to entertaine and nouriſhe them, to frame your hilles, to maintayne them, and to pull them downe, to cutte, to faſhion, to erect, and to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:3359:11"/> ſerue your Poales, to gather, to drye, and to packe your Hoppes, with manye other circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances neceſſarily appertaining hervnto. Final<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye, you muſt be taught the reformation of many enormities and abuſes whyche are receyued in moſt places for good rules, the which (God wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling) I will ſet forth truly according to the notes of experience, although not learnedlye after the rules of Rhetoricke.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of the preparation of a Hoppe Garden.</head>
               <p>YOu muſt lay forth the grounde which you determine to imploye this waye, in as le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell, ſquare, and vniforme wyſe as you maye.</p>
               <p>If your grounde be graſſye, roughe, or ſtyffe, it ſhould be firſt ſowen with Hempe, or Beanes, which naturally maketh the grounde moolowe, deſtroyeth weedes, and neuertheleſſe leaueth the ſame in good ſeaſon for this purpoſe.</p>
               <p>But in what plight or ſtate ſoeuer youre grounde be, tyll it, in the beginning of Winter with the Plough, if it be great, or with the ſpade, if it be ſmall, and this doe, not only the yeare be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore you plant it, but alſo euery yeare after, euen ſo long as you meane to receyue the vttermoſt commoditie of your Garden, aſſuring your ſelfe that the more paynes you take, and the more coſt you beſtowe rightly herevpon, the more you doe
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:3359:11"/> double your profite, and the nearer you reſemble the trade of the Flemming.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The tyme to cut and ſet Hoppe Rootes.</head>
               <p>IN the ende of Marche, or in the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of Aprill, repayre to ſome good Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den orderly kept, as wherein the Hoppes are all of a good kynde, all yerely cut, and wherin all the hylles are rayſed very high, (for there the rootes will be greateſt) then compounde with the owner or keeper thereof for choyce rootes, which in ſome places will coſt ſixe pence an hundreth, but commonly they ſhall be giuen vnto you, ſo as you cut them your ſelfe, and leaue euery hyll or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derly and fully dreſſed, but what order you ſhall vſe herein, I will hereafter ſhewe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Rules for the choyce and preparation of Rootes.</head>
               <p>ANd now you muſt chooſe the biggeſt rootes you can finde (that is to ſay) ſuch as are in bigneſſe three or foure inches about.</p>
               <p>And let euery roote which you ſhall prouide to ſet, be nine or ten ynches long.</p>
               <p>Let there be contayned in euerye ſuch roote, three ioyntes.</p>
               <p>Let all your rootes be but the ſpringes of the yeare laſt paſt.</p>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:3359:12"/>
               <p>You muſt haue great regarde that you cumber not your Garden with wylde Hoppes.</p>
               <p>Wylde Hoppes are not to be diſcerned from the good, by the rootes, but eyther by the fruite, or by the ſtalke.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of the good Hoppe.</head>
               <p>THe good and the kindely Hoppe beareth a great and a greene ſtalke, a large and a harde bell.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of the vnkindly Hoppe.</head>
               <p>THe Hoppe that lykes not his entertayne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, namely his ſeate, his grounde, his keeper, his dunge, or the maner of his ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting. &amp;c. appeareth at the firſt out of the grounde greene and ſmall in ſtalke, thicke and roughe in leaues, verye like vnto a Nettle, which will be commonly deuoured, or much bytten with a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle black flie, who alſo will doe harme vnto good Hoppes where the Garden ſtandeth bleake, or the Hoppe ſpringeth rath, but be not diſcomfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted herewith, for the heate of the Sommer will reforme this matter, and the later Springs will be little annoyed with this Flie, who (though ſhe leaue the leaſe as full of holes as a nette) yet ſhe ſeldome proceedeth to the vtter deſtruction of the Hoppe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:3359:12"/>
               <head>Of the wylde Hoppe.</head>
               <p>OF the wylde Hoppe, the fruite is eyther altogither ſeede, or elſe looſe and light belles, the ſtalke is redde, howbeit, here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the difference betweene the good and the badde Hoppe is not to be diſcerned, vntill the ſtalke be twoo or three yardes high, for at their firſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming vp, the one as well as the other appeareth redde, and the beſt Hoppe is then the reddeſt.</p>
               <p>Prouide your rootes therfore, where you are before hande aſſured of their goodneſſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of ſetting of Hoppe rootes.</head>
               <p>HAuing made your prouiſion of rootes in this wiſe, returne therewith to your Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den ſpeedilye, and eyther ſet them immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately, or lay them in ſome Puddle neare there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto, or burie them in the grounde vntill conue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niencie of winde, weather, and leyſure (the want whereof may ſometimes preuent good expedici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on) ſhall ſerue. Prouided alwayes that you leaue them not in water or Puddle aboue .xxiiij. hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res, but in the earth you may leaue them as long as the time of ſetting endureth.</p>
               <p>Your Garden being dreſſed, as before I adui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed you, it ſhall be eaſie for you to direct your hils aright, and that in equall diſtance, with a Poale, or rather with a lyne (that will not ſtretche) ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:3359:13"/> therevppon ſhorte threedes, or placing in it pynnes, according to the proporcion of ſpace which you meane to leaue betweene your hylles, whereof if one be placed out of order, it ſhall ble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſhe and hurt a great part of your Garden.</p>
               <p>If your Garden be one acte in bigneſſe, &amp; lye ſquare, leaue betweene euery hole, three yardes, or eight foote at the leaſt in ſpace, as well that the hilles may be made the greater, &amp; that the Hops of one Poale reache not to another, as alſo that the Sunne may the more freely and vniuerſally paſſe through your Garden, which by this mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes may yearely be plowed betwixt the hylles, whereas otherwiſe it muſt be digged, a more te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious and coſtly buſineſſe.</p>
               <p>If your Garden be very little, you may ſette the hilles ſomewhat nearer togither, namely, ſeauen foote a ſunder.</p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>pins and line for planting hops</figDesc>
               </figure>
               <p>Your lyne being layde leuell, you muſt dygge vnderneath euery threede or pinne placed vpon the ſame, a hole like to a Pitfall, one foote ſquare, and one foote deepe.</p>
               <p>When you haue made twenty or thirty holes, take vp ſo many rootes, from where you beſtow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed them, as ought to be ſet therein, and go to woorke on this wiſe, alwayes watching a tyme (if you maye) that the wynde be in ſome part of the South or Weſt, but be not ſo ſcrupulous
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:3359:13"/> herein, that you ouerſlip the Moneth of Aprill, leaſt Salomons ſaying be ſpoken of you: <hi>Hee that regardeth the wynde ſhall not ſowe,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Eccle. 11.</note> 
                  <hi>and hee that hath reſpect to the Clowdes ſhall not reape.</hi> For hee that neglecteth the Moneth of Aprill, ſhall haue a bad ſeaſon to cut or plant Hoppes.</p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>bundling hop roots</figDesc>
               </figure>
               <p>Take twoo or three of your rootes (which by this time will yeelde forth greene ſciences or buds, and will alſo haue ſmall rootes or beardes growing out of them, the which muſt be all pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red awaye harde by the olde roote) ioyne them cloſe togither, ſo as (in any wiſe) they may be e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen in the toppes, ſet them alſo altogither bolte vpright, directlye vnder the foreſayde threede or pinne, holding them harde togither with the one hand, while you fyll the hole with the other, with fyne moulde prepared and layde readye before hande, regarding that the toppes of the rootes be leuell wyth the face or vppermoſt part of the grounde.</p>
               <p>Take good heede alſo that you ſet not that ende downewarde, that grew before vpwarde, which you ſhal know by the buddes that appeare in the knots of ech roote, &amp; let no part of the deade ſtalk
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:3359:14"/> remayne vpon the vppermoſt ioynt thereof.</p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>man planting hops</figDesc>
               </figure>
               <p>And here is to be noted, that the readyeſt and eueneſt waye, is alwayes to ſet your rootes at one certayne corner of the hole, which corner ſhoulde alwayes be right vnderneath the ſayde pinne or threede, as is afore ſhewed.</p>
               <p>At this time you muſt make no hill at all, but onely couer the toppes of your rootes about twoo ynches thick, with the fineſt moulde you can get.</p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>man planting hops</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Abuſes and diſorders in ſetting.</head>
               <p>SOme vſe to ſette at euerye corner of the hole one roote, but this is a naughtie and a tedious trade, bicauſe a man ſhall bee longer in dreſſing one of theſe, than about foure other. To be ſhort, you ſhall this way ſo cumber both your ſelfe and your Garden, that you will ſoone be wearye with woorking, and your Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den as ſoone wearie of bearing.</p>
               <p>Some wynde them, and ſet both endes vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde, and herein both the cunning of the work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, and the goodneſſe of the rootes, are togither very liuely expreſſed, for if the rootes were good, they coulde not ſo be wounde, or if the workman were ſkylfull, hee woulde not be ſo fonde to ſet them in that order.</p>
               <p>Some vſe to laye them thwart or flat, but I ſaye flatlye, that the ſame is an ouerthwart and propoſterous way, for they can neyther proſper well, (as being ſet contrarye to their nature and kind of growing) nor be kept as they ought to be.</p>
               <p>Some vſe to make hylles, and then ſet their rootes therein, but theſe conclude themſelues from miniſtring ſuccour vnto them at anye time after, beſides manye inconueniences hereby en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuing.</p>
               <p>Some ſet their rootes, and then burie them
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:3359:15"/> with a great hyll made vppon them, and this is all one with the other, ſauing that the hill ſo cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth theſe, as moſt commonlye they growe not at all.</p>
               <p>Finally, there be as many euill wayes to ſet, as there be ignorant men to deuyſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Prouiſion agaynſt annoyance, and ſpoyle of your Garden.</head>
               <p>IF your Garden be ſmall, and verye nigh to your houſe, you may arme euerye hill with a fewe thornes, to defend them from the annoyance of Poultrie, which manye times will ſcrape and bathe amonge the hylles, and ſo diſcouer and hurt the Springes, but a Gooſe is the moſte noyſome vermine that can enter into this Garden, for (beſides the Allegorie that may be applyed in this caſe) a Gooſe will brut vppon euery yong ſcience or Hoppe budde, that appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth out of the grounde, which neuer will growe afterwardes, and therefore as well to auoyde the Gooſe, as other noyſome cattell, let your clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure be made ſtrong, and kept ryght.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶Of Poales.</head>
               <p>IT remayneth that I ſpeake nowe of Poales, bicauſe poaling is the next work nowe to be done.</p>
               <p>If your hilles be diſtant three yardes a ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:3359:15"/> prouide for euery hill foure Poales, if you will make your hilles nearer togither, three Poales ſhall ſuffice.</p>
               <p>And note that in the firſt yeare you muſt oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupie as manye Poales as in anye yeare after, the reaſon whereof I will declare in the tytle of Hilles. &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Alder Poales are beſt for this purpoſe, as wherevnto the Hoppes ſeeme moſte willinglye and naturally to encline, bicauſe both the faſhion of theſe Poales being as a Taper ſmall aboue, and great belowe, and alſo the roughneſſe of the Alder ryne, ſtayth the Hoppe ſtalke more firme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly from ſlyding downe, than either Aſhe or Oke, which for continuance be ſomewhat better, how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beit, theſe with the order that I ſhall preſcrybe, will endure ſixe or ſeauen yeares.</p>
               <p>Theſe are alſo beſt cheape, and eaſieſt to bee gotten in moſt places, and ſooneſt growen readye for this purpoſe.</p>
               <p>There is in the Springs of theſe, leaſt daun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger in growing, or in being deſtroyed, or bitten by cattell.</p>
               <p>Finallye, by the expence of theſe, there enſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth leaſt annoyaunce to the common wealth, as well for the cauſes aforeſayde, as alſo bicauſe they growe not in ſo great quantitie, to ſo good timber, nor for ſo many purpoſes as eyther Oke or Aſhe.</p>
               <p>The beſt tyme to cutte your Poales, is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene All hallowentyde and Chriſtmas, but
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:3359:16"/> you muſt pyle them vp immediatly after they are cut ſharped, reformed in length, and ſmoothed, leaſt they rotte before you occupie them.</p>
               <p>You may not leaue any ſcragges vpon them, the reaſon whereof you ſhall conceyue in the ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle of gathering Hoppes.</p>
               <p>Your Poales may not be aboue .xv. or .xvj. foote long at the moſt, except your ground be ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry rich, and that you haue added therevnto great labor in rayſing vp your hilles, and alſo except your hilles ſtande to neare togither, if theſe three things meete in one Garden, the beſt way of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation, is to ſet the fewer Poales to an hyll, or to let them remaine the longer. Otherwiſe the Hoppes will growe from one poale to another, and ſo ouerſhadow your Garden, the fault ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of being onely to be imputed to the neereneſſe of the hilles. But hereof ſhall be ſayde more in the tytle of Reformacions.</p>
               <p>The Hoppe neuer ſtocketh kindely, vntill it reache higher than the Poale, and returne from it a yarde or two, for whyleſt it tendeth clyming vpwarde, the braunches which growe out of the principall ſtalke (wherein conſiſteth the abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of encreaſe) growe little or nothing.</p>
               <p>Let the quantitie of your Poales be great (that is to ſay) nine or tenne ynches about at the lower ende, ſo ſhall they endure the longer, and withſtande the winde the better.</p>
               <p>To deſcrybe the pryce of Poales, or what it will coſt you to furniſhe a Garden conteyning
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:3359:16"/> one acre of grounde, it were a harde matter, bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the place altereth the pryce of woode. But in a Wayne you maye carye a hundreth and fyftie Poales, and I ſee ſmall cauſe why a loade of theſe ſhoulde be dearer than a loade of any other woode.</p>
               <p>After the firſt yeare Poales will be nothing chargeable vnto you, for you maye eyther picke them out of your owne prouiſion of Fuell, or buye them of your neyghbours that haue no oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion to applye them this way. For, the yearely ſupply of twoo loades of Poales, will maintayne one acre continually.</p>
               <p>Your rotten and broken Poales will doe you good ſeruice, for the kindling of your fiers in the Oſte, wherevpon you ſhould drie your Hoppes, and they ſhould be preſerued chiefly for that pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe.</p>
               <p>At Poppering (where both ſcarcitie and expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience hath taught them to make prouiſion here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of) they doe commonlye at the Eaſt and North ſide of their Gardens, ſet and preſerue Alders, wherewith they continually maintaine them.</p>
               <p>Before you ſet vp your Poales, laye them all alongſt your Garden betweene euerye rowe of hilles by three or fower togither, I meane beſide euery hill ſo many Poales as you determine to ſet thereon, ſo ſhall you make the more ſpeede in your woorke.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:3359:17"/>
               <head>Of the erection of Poales.</head>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>two tools</figDesc>
               </figure>
               <p>You muſt ſet euerye Poale a foote and a halfe deepe, and within twoo or three ynches at the moſt of the principall roote.</p>
               <p>If your grounde be rockie and ſhallowe, tarie the longer before you ſet vp your Poales, ſo as your Hoppes maye be growen two or three foote high, that you may aduenture to make a hyll or banke at euery Poale to ſtaye and vpholde the
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:3359:17" rendition="simple:additions"/> ſame, wythoute burying anye of the yoonger ſprings, which may afterwarde be couered with leſſe danger and annoyance to the principal roote.</p>
               <p>Let the Poales of euery hyll leane a little out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde one from another, as is hereafter ſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wed.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of Ramming of Poales.</head>
               <p>THen with a péece of woode as bygge be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowe as the great ende of one of youre Poales, ramme the earth that lyeth at the
<figure>
                     <figDesc>man inserting three poles into planted hops</figDesc>
                  </figure> out ſide of the Poale, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto, but med<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle not within the compaſſe of youre Poales, as they are pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, leaſt you ſpoile the ſprin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of Reparation of Poales.</head>
               <p>IF any of your Poales chaunce to breake when the Hoppe is growen vp, ſome vſe tenderly to vndooe and pull away the bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken Poale, and to tye the toppe of thoſe Hoppes to the toppe of a newe Poale, then wynding it a
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:3359:18"/> turne or two about according to the courſe of the Sunne, to ſet it in the hole, or beſides the hole where the broken Poale ſtoode, and ſome other being loth to take ſo much paynes, turne it about ſome of the other Poales that ſtande vppon the ſame hille, and ſo leaue it. But the beſt waye is, to ſet a newe Poale beſide the broken Poale, and to tye the broken Poale to the ſame, whiche may vpholde the ſayde broken Poale, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue the Hoppe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of the preſeruation of Poales.</head>
               <p>ANd although we are not yet come to the laying vp of Poales, I am bolde herein, as I began to late, ſo to make an ende to rathe, bicauſe I woulde couch the whole matter of Poales togither, laying them by themſelues (I meane) comprehending vnder one tytle, the buſineſſe appertayning vnto them.</p>
               <p>For the preſeruation and better continuance of Poales, ſome make houſes of purpoſe, and laye them vp therein.</p>
               <p>Some ſet them vpright to a tree, and ouer them make a penthouſe of boowes or boordes.</p>
               <p>Some lay a great heape of Hoppeſtalkes vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon the grounde, and vppon them a great heape of Poales, and vpon the Poales againe lay an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other heape of ſtalkes. &amp;c.</p>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:3359:18" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <p>Theſe men doe hereby expreſſe no great ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience, although by their diligence they ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fye a good deſire.</p>
               <p>You ſhall neede to doe no more but thus. At the endes or ſydes of your Garden, take three Poales ſtanding vpon three hilles placed direct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye one by another, and three like Poales vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon three other hilles of the next rowe right ouer againſt them, conſtrayne them to meete togither by two and two in the toppes, and ſo holde them till one with a forked wande maye put three Withes (like vnto three Broome bandes) which muſt be made of the ſtalkes of Hoppes, vppon eache couple of the ſayde ſixe Poales, ſo ſhall the ſame ſixe Poales being ſo bounde by two and two togither, ſtande like the roofe or rafters of an houſe.</p>
               <p>To keepe the Poales that ſhall lye nether<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſte from rotting, by the moyſtneſſe of the grounde: vſe within the compaſſe of your ſayde ſixe hils, (vnderneath the Poales that you haue faſtened togither in the tops,) to rayſe three little bankes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> thwart from hyll to hyll, as though you woulde make your ſixe hylles to bee but three.</p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>two men building a shelter for planted hops</figDesc>
               </figure>
               <p>If you thinke that you haue not Poales ynowe to fylle the roume, pull downe the Wyths or bandes lower, &amp; your roume will be leſſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶Of tying of Hoppes to the <hi>Poales.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>WHen your Hoppes are growne about one or twoo foote high, bynde vp (with a Ruſhe or a Graſſe) ſuch as declyne from the Poales, wynding them as often about the ſame Poales as you can, and directing them al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes according to the courſe of the Sunne, but doe it not in the morning when the dewe remay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth vpon them, if your leyſure may ſerue to doe it at any other time of the day.</p>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:3359:19"/>
               <p>If you laye ſofte greene Ruſhes abroade in the dewe and the Sunne, within twoo or three dayes, they will be lythie, tough, and handſome for this purpoſe of tying, which may not be fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlowed,
<figure>
                     <figDesc>man tying plant stems to poles</figDesc>
                  </figure> for it is moſt certaine that the Hoppe that lyeth long vpon the grounde before he be tyed to the Poale, proſpereth nothing ſo wel as it, which ſooner attayneth therevnto.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶Of hylling and hylles.</head>
               <p>NOwe you muſt begyn to make your hils, and for the better dooing therof, you muſt prepare a toole of Iron faſhioned ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what like to a Coopers Addes,<note place="margin">This toole is here aboue better pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portioned, than that on the other ſide following.</note> but not ſo much boowing, and therfore lykeſt to the netherpart of a ſhoouell, the powle whereof muſt be made with a round hole to receyue a helue, lyke to the helue of a Mattocke, and in the powle alſo a nayle hole muſt be made, to faſten it to the helue.</p>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:3359:20" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <p>This helue ſhoulde boowe ſomewhat lyke to a Sythe, or to the ſteale of a Sythe, and it muſt be lyttle more than a yarde long.</p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>scythe</figDesc>
               </figure>
               <p>Some thinke it impertinent and not neceſſary to make hylles the firſt yere, partly bicauſe their diſtruſt of this yeares profite quallifyeth their diligence in this behalfe, and partly for that they thinke that the principall roote proſpereth beſt, when there be no newe rootes out of them for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced and mayntained. But experience confuteth both theſe coniectures, for by induſtrie, the firſt yeares profite will be great, and thereby alſo the principall ſettes much amended, as their proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie in the ſeconde yeare will plainely appeare.</p>
               <p>But in this worke you muſt be both paynefull and curious, as wherein conſiſteth the hope of your gaynes and the ſucceſſe of your worke. For the greater in quantitie you make your hylles, the more in number you ſhall haue of youre Hoppes, and the fewer weedes you ſhall haue on your grounde, the more Hoppes you ſhall haue vpon your Poales.</p>
               <p>In conſideration whereof, I ſay, your labour muſt be continuall from this time till the time of
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:3359:20"/> gathering, in rayſing your hylles and cleering your grounde from weedes.</p>
               <p>In the firſt yeare that you plant your Hoppe-garden, ſuppreſſe not one ſcience, but ſuffer them all to clyme vp to the Poales, for if you ſhoulde burie or couer all the ſprings of any one of your three rootes, which you did latelye ſet, the roote thereof periſheth, and perhaps out of ſome one roote there will not proceede aboue one or twoo ſpringes, which being buryed, that roote I ſaye dyeth, and therefore the more poales are at thys time requiſite.</p>
               <p>After the firſt yeare you muſt not ſuffer aboue twoo or three ſtalkes at the moſt to growe vp to one Poale, but put downe and bury all the reſt.</p>
               <p>Howbeit, you may let them all grow till they be foure or fyue foote high at the leaſt, whereby you ſhall make the better choyce of them which you meane to maintaine, whereby alſo the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall roote will be the better. &amp;c</p>
               <p>Some ſuffer their Hoppes to clyme vp to the toppes of the Poales, and then make the hilles at one inſtant of ſuch quantitie as they meane to leaue them, which is neyther the beſt nor the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conde waye.</p>
               <p>But if (for expedition) you be driuen here vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, begin ſooner (that is to ſay) when the Hoppes be foure or fyue foote long, and afterwardes if leyſure ſhall ſerue, refreſhe them againe wyth more earth.</p>
               <p>But to make them well, and as they ought to
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:3359:21" rendition="simple:additions"/> be made, you muſt immediatly after your poales are ſet, make a little banke or circle rounde a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the outſide of them, as a mention how wide your hyll ſhall be, and as a receptacle to retayne and keepe moyſture, wherof there cannot lightly come to much, ſo it come from aboue.</p>
               <p>If your Garden be great, by that time that you haue made an end of theſe circles or banks, it will be time to proceede further towardes the buylding vp of your hylles.</p>
               <p>Nowe therefore returne agayne to the place where you beganne, or elſe where you ſee the Hoppes higheſt, and with your toole pare of the vppermoſt earth from the Alleys or ſpaces be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene the hylles, and laye the ſame to your Hoppes, vppon and within the circle that you made before, alwayes leauing the ſame higheſt of any part of the hill, and ſo paſſe through your Garden againe and againe, till you haue rayſed your hylles by little and little, to ſo great a quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titie as is before declared, and looke howe highe your hylles is, ſo long are your newe rootes, and the longer your newe rootes or ſpringes be, the more larger and better your Hoppes will be.</p>
               <p>Great and ouergrowen weedes ſhoulde not be layd vpon the hylles, as to rayſe them to their due quantitie, but when with diligence and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pedition you paſſe through your Garden, conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually paring away eche greene thing aſſoone as it appeareth, you ſhall doe well, with the ſame; and the vppermoſte moulde of your Garden
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:3359:21"/> togither, to maintaine and encreaſe the ſubſtance of your hylles, euen till they be almoſt a yarde highe.</p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>man tending to high plants with long tools</figDesc>
               </figure>
               <p>In the firſte yeare make not your hyll to rathe, leaſt in the dooing therof you oppreſſe ſome of thoſe ſpringes which woulde otherwiſe haue appeared out of the grounde.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Abuſes in hylling.</head>
               <p>SOme obſerue no time, and ſome no mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure in making their hylles, but (hauing
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:3359:22"/> hearde ſay that hylles are neceſſarye) they make them they care not when nor howe.</p>
               <p>Some make hylles once for all, and neuer after plucke downe the ſame, but better it were to make no hill, than ſo to doe, for after the firſt yeare it doth derogate, &amp; not adde any comfort to the roote, if it be not newe made and dreſſed. &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Some vſe to breake off the toppes of the Hoppes when they are growen a .xj. or .xij. foote high, bicauſe thereby they barniſh and ſtocke ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedingly, wherein though I cannot commende their dooings, yet doe they much better than ſuch as will haue their Poales as longe as their Hoppes.</p>
               <p>But if your Poale be very long, and that the Hoppe haue not attayned to the toppe therof be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the midſt of Iuly, you ſhall doe well then to breake or cut of the toppe of the ſame Hoppe, for ſo ſhall the reſidue of the growing tyme ſerue to the maintenance and encreaſe of the braunches, which otherwiſe woulde expyre without dooing any good in that matter, bicauſe that whole time woulde then be employed to the lengthening of the ſtalke, which little preuayleth (I ſay) to the ſtocking or increaſe of the Hoppe.</p>
               <p>And here is to be noted that many couetous men, thinking (in haſte) to enlarge their lucre, doe fynde (at leyſure) their commoditie dimini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed, whyleſt they make their hylles to thicke, their Poales to long, and ſuffer to many ſtalkes to growe vppon one Poale, wherein (I ſaye)
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:3359:22" rendition="simple:additions"/> whyle they runne awaye flattering themſelues with the imagination of double gaynes, they are ouertaken with treble dammage (that is to ſay) with the loſſe of their time, their labour, and their coſt.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶Of the gathering of Hoppes.</head>
               <p>AT what time (or rather before) that your Hoppes begyn to chaunge colour (that is to ſay) ſomewhat before Michaelmas, you muſt gather them, and for the ſpeedyer diſpatch thereof, procure as much helpe as you can, ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king the aduantage of fayre weather.</p>
               <p>To doe the ſame in the readyeſt and beſt or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, you muſt pull downe foure hylles ſtanding togither in the middeſt of your Garden, cut the rootes of all thoſe hilles as you ſhall be taught in the Tytle of Cutting. &amp;c. Then pare the ſame plot, leuell it, throwe water on it, treade it, and ſweepe it, ſo ſhall it be a fayre floore, whereon the Hoppes muſt lye to be picked.</p>
               <p>Then beginning neare vnto the ſame, cut the ſtalkes a ſunder cloſe by the toppes of the hylles, and if the Hoppes of one Poale be growen faſt vnto another, cutte them alſo a ſunder with a ſharpe hooke.</p>
               <p>You may make the Forke and Hooke (which cutteth a ſunder the Hoppes that grow togither) here is inſtrument to ſerue both theſe turnes, as as is here after ſhewed.</p>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:3359:23"/>
               <p>Then you may with the forked ende, thruſt vp, or ſhooue off, all ſuch ſtalkes as remayne vpon eche Hoppe Poale, and carie them to the floore prepared for that purpoſe.</p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>two men removing plants from poles</figDesc>
               </figure>
               <p>For the better dooing hereof, it is very neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie that your Poales be ſtreyght without ſcrags or knobbes.</p>
               <p>In any wiſe cut no more ſtalks than you ſhall cary away within one houre or twoo at the moſt, for if in the meane time the Sunne ſhyne hote, or if it happen to rayne, the Hoppes (remayning cut in that ſorte) will be much impayred thereby.</p>
               <p>Let all ſuch as helpe you, ſtande rounde about the floore, and ſuffer them not to pyngle in pic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king one by one, but let them ſpeedily ſtrype them into Baſkets prepared ready therefore.</p>
               <p>It is not hurtfull greatly though the ſmaller leaues be mingled with the Hoppes.</p>
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:3359:23"/>
               <p>Remember alwayes to cleere your floore twice or thryce euery day, and ſweepe it cleane at euery ſuch time, before you go to woorke againe.</p>
               <p>If the wether be vnlyke to be fayre, you may carie theſe Hoppes into your houſe in Blankets or Baſkets. &amp;c. and there accompliſh this work. Vſe no lynnen hereabouts, for the Hoppes will ſtayne it ſo, as it can neuer be waſhed out.</p>
               <p>If your Poales be ſcraggye, ſo as you can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſtryppe the ſtalkes from them in this order, you muſt pull them vppe with mayne force, and this is paynefull to your ſelfe, hurtfull to your Hoppes, and a delaye to your worke.</p>
               <p>Then muſt you lay theſe Poales vpon a cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of forked ſtakes driuen into the grounde, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing twoo or three yardes diſtant one from ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, as Spittes vpon Raunges, and ſo diſpatch this buſineſſe if the wether be fayre, if it be lyke to be fowle, you muſt be fayne to carie the Hops togither with the Poales into your Barne or houſe.</p>
               <p>In any wiſe let not the Hoppes be wet when you cut them from the hylles, neyther make any delay of gathering after the ſame tyme of cut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, for in ſtanding abroade they will ſhed their ſeede, wherein conſiſteth the chiefe vertue of the Hoppe, and hereof I cannot warne you to often, nor to earneſtly.</p>
               <p>Nowe by order I ſhoulde declare vnto you, the manner of drying your Hoppes, but bicauſe I muſt therwithall deſcrybe the places meete for
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:3359:24"/> that purpoſe, with manye circumſtances apper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayning therevnto, I will be bolde firſt to finiſh the worke within your Hoppe garden, and then to leade you out of the ſame, into the place where you muſt drye your Hoppes. &amp;c.</p>
               <p>When your Hoppes are gathered, aſſoone as you haue leyſure, take vp your Poales and pyle them (that remaine good) as I haue ſhewed you in the tytle of Poales.</p>
               <p>Then carie out your broken Poales, and the Hoppe ſtrawe to the fyre.</p>
               <p>Nowe may you depart out of your Garden, tyll the Marche following, except in the meane time you will bring in dunge or good earth to the maintenance therof, towards the heigthening of your hylles, or elſe will plowe it. &amp;c.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>What there is to be done in <hi>Win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter herein.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>TO be curious in laying dunge vpon the hylles in Winter, as to comfort or warme the rootes (as ſome doe) it ſhall be neede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe, rather plucke downe the hylles, and let the rootes lye bare all the Winter ſeaſon, and this is vſually done where Hoppes are beſt ordered, eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially to reſtrayne them from to rathe ſpryn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging.</p>
               <p>If the grounde be great that you keepe, you ſhall be driuen ſo to doe, otherwiſe you ſhall not be able to ouercome your worke in due time.</p>
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:3359:24"/>
               <p>In any caſe you muſt auoyde new horſedung as a very noyſome and pernicious thing for your Hoppes.</p>
               <p>Stall dung is the beſt that can be wyſhed for to ſerue this turne, ſo it be throughly rotten.</p>
               <p>Rather vſe no dunge than vnrotten dunge a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the dreſſing of your Hoppes, but omit not to bring into your Garden dung that maye there be preſerued till it be good, or needefull to be v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶The order for reforming your <hi>grounde.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>IN March you ſhall returne to your Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den, and finde it repleniſhed with weedes, except by tillage. &amp;c. you haue preuented that matter already. It muſt (as well therefore, as bicauſe the earth maye be the more fyne, and eaſie to be deliuered vnto the hylles) be digged ouer or plowed.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶The order of cutting Hoppe <hi>Rootes.</hi>
               </head>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>man cutting back plant roots</figDesc>
               </figure>
               <p>In the dooing hereof be carefull that you ſpoyle not the olde ſettes, as for the other rootes which are to be cut awaye, you ſhall not neede to ſpare them to the delay of your worke.</p>
               <p>Take heede that you vncouer not anye more than the toppes of the olde ſettes in the firſt yere of cutting.</p>
               <p>At what time ſo euer you pull downe your hylles, cut not your rootes before the ende of March, or in the beginning of Aprill, and then remember the wynde.</p>
               <p>In the firſt yeare (I meane) at the fyrſt time of cutting and dreſſing of your rootes, you muſt (with a ſharpe knyfe) cut awaye all ſuch rootes or ſpringes as grewe the ye are before, out of your ſettes, within one ynch of the ſame.</p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>man cutting back plant roots</figDesc>
               </figure>
               <p>There grow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth oute of the olde ſettes cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne Rootes ryght downe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes not ioynted at all, which ſerue onely for the nouriſhing and comfort of thoſe ſets or prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall rootes: there be other lyke vnto them growing outwarde at the ſides of the ſettes.</p>
               <p>If they be not met withall, and cut a ſunder, they will encumber your whole Garden.</p>
               <p>Bicauſe it maye ſeeme harde to diſcerne the olde ſettes from the newe ſpringes, I thought good to aduertiſe you howe eaſye a thing it is to ſee the difference therof, for fyrſt you ſhall be ſure to fynde your ſettes where you did ſet them, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing encreaſed in length, but ſomewhat in big<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe enlarged, and in few yeares all your ſettes will be growen into one, ſo as by the quantitie that thing ſhall plainely appeare: and laſtlye the difference is ſeene by the colour, the olde roote being redde, the other whyte, but if the hylles be not yearely pulled downe, and the rootes yeare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly cut, then in deede the olde ſettes ſhall not bee perceyued from the other rootes.</p>
               <p>If your ſettes be ſmall, and placed in good
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:3359:26" rendition="simple:additions"/> grounde, the hyll well mayntained, the newe rootes will be greater than the olde.</p>
               <p>If there growe in any hyll a wylde Hoppe, or whenſoeuer the ſtalke waxeth redde, or when the Hoppe in any wiſe decayeth, pull vp euerye roote in that hill, and ſet newe in their places, at the vſuall time of cutting and ſetting.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of diuers mens follyes.</head>
               <p>MAny men ſeeing the ſprings ſo forward, as they will be by this time, are loth to loſe the aduauntage thereof, and more vnwilling to cut awaye ſo many goodlye rootes, but they that are daungerous in this behalfe, take pitie vpon their owne profyte, and are lyke vnto them that refrayne to laye dung vpon their corne lande, bicauſe they woulde not beraye it with ſo vncleanlye a thing.</p>
               <p>And ſome that take vppon them great ſkyll herein, thynke that for the fyrſte yeare they maye be left vnhilled and vncutte. &amp;c. deceyuing themſelues wyth this conceypte, that then the ſettes proſper beſt wythin the grounde when they ſende leaſt of their nature and ſtate out of the grounde. In this reſpect alſo they pull a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waye or ſuppreſſe all ſuch ſprings (as ſoone as they appeare) which growe more, and beſides them which they meane to aſſigne to each Poale, as though when a mans fingers were cutte off, his hande woulde growe the greater. In deede
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:3359:26"/> if there be no hyll maintayned, then the moe ſpringes are ſuffered to growe from out of the principall roote, the more burden and puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment it wil be to the ſame. But when the ſprings are maintayned with a hill, ſo much as remay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth within the ſame is conuerted into rootes, which rather adde than take awaye anye ſtate from the principall roote, in conſideration hereof, the ſuppreſſing of the ſpringes maye not be too rathe, for whatſoeuer opinion be hereof recey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, the many ſpringes neuer hurt the principall roote, if the hylles be well mayntained, but it is the cumbring and ſhadowing of one to another that woorketh the annoyance.</p>
               <p>When you haue cut your Hoppes, you muſt couer them as you were taught in the tytle of ſetting, and proceede according to the order alre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dye ſet downe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of diſorders and maintayners thereof.</head>
               <p>SOme there be that deſpyſe good order, being deceyued with a ſhewe of increaſe which ſometimes appeareth in a diſorde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red grounde, to them I ſay and ſay it truly, that the ſame is a bad and a ſmall increaſe in reſpect of the other.</p>
               <p>I ſaye alſo that although diſorderly dooings at the firſt may haue a countenance of good ſucceſſe, yet in fewe yeares the ſame, and all hope thereof will certainly decay.</p>
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:3359:27"/>
               <p>Some other there be that deſpiſe good order, ſatiſfying themſelues with this, that they haue ſufficiently to ſerue their owne turne, wythout all theſe troubles, and ſurelye it were pittie that theſe ſhoulde be troubled with any great abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daunce, that in contempt of their owne profite, and of the common welth, neglect ſuch a benefite profered vnto them.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶Of an Oste.</head>
               <p>NOwe haue I ſhewed vnto you the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect platforme of a Hoppe garden, out of the which I led you for a time, &amp; brought you in againe when tyme required, and there woulde I leaue you about your buſineſſe, were it not to ſhew you by deſcription ſuch an Oſte as they drie their Hoppes vpon at Poppering, with the order thereof. &amp;c. Which for the ſmall charges and trouble in drying, for the ſpeedie and well drying, and for the handſome and eaſie dooing thereof, may be a profytable patterne, and a ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarie inſtruction for as many as haue, or ſhall haue to doe herein.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of the ſeuerall Roumes for an Oſte.</head>
               <p>FIrſt a little houſe muſt be buylt, of length xviij. or .xix. foote, of wydeneſſe eyght, wherein muſt be comprehended three ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerall roumes.</p>
               <p>The myddle and principall roume muſt be for your Oſte, eight foote ſquare. The forepart which
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:3359:27" rendition="simple:additions"/> is to containe your greene Hoppes, and the hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der part which muſt receyue your dryed Hops, will fall out to be fyue foote long, and eyght foote wyde a peece.</p>
               <p>The chiefe matters that are to be by mee deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crybed herein, are the Furnace belowe wherein the fyre is to be made, and the bed aboue where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Hoppes muſt lye to be dryed: this I haue chieflye to aduiſe you of, that you buylde the whole houſe and euery part thereof as cloſe as you can, and to place it neare to your Garden for the better expedicion of your woorke, and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what diſtant from your houſe to auoyde the dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of fyre.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of the Furnace or Keele.</head>
               <p>THe floore or nether part of your Furnace muſt be about thirteene ynches wyde.</p>
               <p>The depth or heygth thereof muſt alſo be thirteene ynches.</p>
               <p>The length of it muſt be about ſixe or ſeauen foote (that is to ſaye) reaching from the forepart of the Oſte almoſt to the further ende thereof, ſo as there be left no more roume but as a manne may paſſe betweene the wall and the ende of it.</p>
               <p>It muſt be made wyde belowe and narrowe aboue faſhioned in outwarde ſhape ſomewhat like to the roofe of an houſe.</p>
               <p>It muſt haue hoales at each ſide, the length of one Bricke a ſunder, and not the bygneſſe of halfe a Bricke, placed checkerwiſe.</p>
               <pb n="40" facs="tcp:3359:28"/>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>furnace</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of the bedde or vpper floore of the Oſte, whereon the Hoppes muſt be dryed.</head>
               <p>THe bedde or vpper floore whereon the Hoppes ſhall lye to be dryed, muſt be pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced fyue foote aboue the nether floore, whereon the furnace ſtandeth.</p>
               <p>The two walles at eche ſide of the houſe ſerue for the bedde to reſt vpon two wayes.</p>
               <p>Nowe muſt two other walles be buylt at ech ende of your Oſte, whereon the other two parts of the bedde muſt reſt, and by this meanes ſhall you haue a cloſe ſquare roume beneath, betwixt the lower floore and the bedde, ſo as the floore be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowe ſhall be as wyde as the bedde aboue.</p>
               <p>Theſe two walles muſt alſo bee made fowre foote aboue the bed (that is to ſay) nine foote high.</p>
               <pb n="41" facs="tcp:3359:28"/>
               <p>At the one ende belowe, beſides the mouth of the furnace, you muſt make a little doore into the roume beneath the bedde. At the other ende a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue the bedde you muſt make a windowe to ſhooue off from the bed the dryed Hoppes, downe into the roume belowe prepared for them.</p>
               <p>The bedde ſhould be made as the bedde of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other Oſte, ſauing that the Rayles or Lathes which ſerue therefore muſt be ſawen verye euen one ynche ſquare, and layde one quarter of an ynche aſunder.</p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>placement of furnace</figDesc>
               </figure>
               <p>And nowe once agayne wiſhing you to make euery doore, windowe, and ioynte of this houſe cloſe, I will leaue buylding, and proceede to the drying of Hoppes, ſauing that I maye not omit to tell you, that you ſhoulde eyther buylde all the walles of this houſe with Bricke, or elſe with Lyme and Haire pargit ouer all the walles, poſtes, and beames thereof, or at the leaſt, that roume wherein the furnace ſtandeth.</p>
               <p>And although I haue delayed you from time, to time, and brought you from place to place, and tediouſly led you in and out, and to and fro in the demonſtration herof, yet muſt I be bold to bring you round about againe, euen to the place where I left you picking, from whence you muſt ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily conuey your pyckt Hoppes to the place built and prepared for them, and with as much ſpeede haſten the drying of them.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The orderly drying of Hoppes.</head>
               <p>THe firſt buſineſſe that is to be done here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, is to go vp to the bedde of the Oſte, and there to receyue Baſkets fylled with Hoppes, at the handes of one that ſtandeth be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowe.</p>
               <p>Then beginning at the further ende (leaſt you ſhoulde treade on them) laye downe Baſketfull by Baſketfull, till the floore or bedde be all coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red,
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:3359:29"/> alwayes ſtirring them euen and leuell, with a Cudgell, ſo as they may lye about a foote and a halfe thicke, and note that vpon this Oſte, there is no Oſte cloth to be vſed.</p>
               <p>Nowe muſt you come downe to make your fyre in the furnace, for the kindling whereof your olde broken Poales are very good, howbeit, for the continuaunce and maintenance of this fyre, that woode is beſt which is not too drie.</p>
               <p>Your Hoppe ſtalkes, or anye other ſtrawe is not to be vſed herein.</p>
               <p>You ſhall not neede to laye the woode through to the farther ende of the furnace, for the fyre made in the forepart therof, will bende that way, ſo as the heate will vniuerſally and indifferently aſcende and proceede out of euery hole.</p>
               <p>You muſt keepe herein a continual and a hote fyre, howbeit, you muſt ſtirre it as little as you can.</p>
               <p>Neyther may you ſtyrre the Hoppes that lye vpon the Oſte, vntill they be throughly dryed.</p>
               <p>When they are drie aboue, then are they redy to be remooued awaye, and yet ſometimes it happeneth that (through the diſorderly laying of them) they are not ſo ſoone drie in one place, as they are in another.</p>
               <p>The waye to helpe that matter, is to take a little Poale (wherewith you ſhall ſenſiblye feele and perceyue which be, and which be not drye, by the ratling of the Hoppes which you ſhall there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with touch) and with the ſame Poale to turne a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:3359:30"/> ſuch Hoppes as be not drie, abating the thickneſſe of the moyſt place.</p>
               <p>When your Hoppes are drie, rake vp the fyre in ſuch ſort as there may be no delay in the renu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thereof.</p>
               <p>Then with expedition ſhooue them out of the windowe before mentioned into the roume pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared to receyue them, with a Rake faſhioned like a Coale Rake, hauing in ſteade of teeth a boorde of one foote broade.</p>
               <p>This being done, goe downe into the lower floore, and ſweepe togither ſuch Hoppes and ſeedes as are fallen thereinto, and laye them vp among the dryed Hoppes, and then without de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lay couer the bedde againe with greene Hoppes and kindle your fyre.</p>
               <p>Laye your dryed Hoppes on a heape togither till they be colde, and by this meanes ſuche as were not perfectlye dryed through ſome diſorder vpon the Oſte, ſhall nowe be reformed.</p>
               <p>If they haue bene well ordered, they will nowe be browne, and yet bright.</p>
               <p>If they be blacke and darcke, it is a note that they are diſordered.</p>
               <p>The Flemings pack them not vp before they ſell them to the Merchant, but lay them in ſome corner of a Loft where they treade them cloſe to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gither.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="45" facs="tcp:3359:30"/>
               <head>Other maners of dryings not ſo good.</head>
               <p>SOme vſe to drye their Hoppes vppon a common Oſte, but that waye there can be no great ſpeede in your woorke, nor ſmall expence of your woode, beſides the daun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of fyre, and yll ſucceſſe of your dooings.</p>
               <p>On this Oſte you muſt haue an Oſte clothe, otherwiſe the ſeede and Hoppes that fall downe ſhall not only periſh, but endaunger the burning of your Oſte.</p>
               <p>Vpon this Oſte you may not lay your Hoppes aboue eyght or nine ynches thicke, which neuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſſe ſhall not be ſo ſoone drie as they which lye vpon the other Oſte almoſt twoo foote thicke, and therfore this waye you ſhall make more toyle in your worke, more ſpoyle in your Hoppes, and more expence in your woode.</p>
               <p>Some vſe to drie their Hoppes in a Garret, or vppon the floore of a Loft or Chamber, in the reproofe whereof I muſt ſaye, that as fewe men haue roume ynough in their houſes to contayne any great quantitie or multitude of Hoppes, ſo the duſt that will ariſe, ſhall empayre them, the chynkes, creuiſes, and open ioyntes of your Loftes being not cloſe byrthed, will deuoure the ſéedes of them, in the ende the leaues will en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>danger them with heating when they are packt, as being not ſo ſoone drie as the Hoppes which
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:3359:31"/> therby ſhall be vtterly ſpoyled in colour, in cent, and in verdure.</p>
               <p>As for anye lowe roumes or earthen floores, they are yet woorſe for this purpoſe than the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, for eyther they yeelde duſt in drythe, or moy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture in wet weather.</p>
               <p>And therefore if you haue no Oſte, drye them in a Loft as open to the ayre as may be, ſweepe, waſh, and rub the boordes, and let your Broome reach to the walles, and euen to the roofe of your Loft, for I can teach you no waye to deuyde the duſt from your Hoppes, but ſo to preuent the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conuenience hereof.</p>
               <p>Stoppe the holes and chynkes of your floore, laye them not aboue halfe a foote thicke, and turne them once a day at the leaſt, by the ſpace of two or three weekes.</p>
               <p>This being done, ſweepe them vp into a cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of your Loft, and there let them lye as long more, for yet there remayneth perill in packing of them.</p>
               <p>If the yeare prooue very wette, your Hoppes aſke the longer time of drying.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The very woorſt way of drying Hoppes.</head>
               <p>SOme lay their Hoppes in the Sunne to drye, and this taketh awaye the ſtate of the Hoppes, and neuertheleſſe leaueth the purpoſe of drying vndone.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="47" facs="tcp:3359:31"/>
               <head>Of not drying.</head>
               <p>SOme gather them, and brue with them being greene and vndryed, ſuppoſing that in drying, the vertue and ſtate of the Hoppe decayeth and fadeth awaye, wherein they are deceyued, for the verdure is woorſe, the ſtrength leſſe, and the quantitie muſt be more of greene Hoppes that are to be brued in this ſort.</p>
               <p>In the fyrſt Woorte which the Bruers call the Hoppewoorte (bicauſe the time of ſeething there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of is ſhort) there goeth out of theſe Hoppes al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt no vertue at all, and therefore experience hath taught them that are driuen to brue wyth theſe greene Hoppes, to ſeeth them agayne in the Woorte, which they call the Ney beere, where af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter long ſeething they will leaue the ſtate whiche remayneth in them, and that is not much.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶Of the packing of Hoppes.</head>
               <p>IN the making of your Hoppeſackes, vſe your owne cunning or inuention, for I haue ſmall ſkill therein, howbeit, I can tell you that the Hoppeſackes that are brought out of Flaunders, may be good ſamplers for you to worke by, the ſtuffe is not daintie wherewith they are made, the Loome is not coſtlye wherein they are wouen, the cunning not curious wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by they are faſhioned, but when you haue them,
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:3359:32"/> and are ready to packe your Hoppes, doe thus.</p>
               <p>Thruſt into the mouth of your ſacke (which muſt be doubled and turned in ſtronglye leaſt it breake) foure ſtrong pynnes halfe a foote long a peece, placed in equall diſtaunce one from the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, then laye two Battes or bygge Poales croſſe or thwart twoo Beames or Couplings of your houſe, which twoo Battes muſt lye no far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther a ſunder than the wydeneſſe of the Sackes mouth. Faſten vpon eche pyn a roape, and knit twoo of thoſe Ropes vppon eche croſſe Batte, ſo as the bottome of the Sacke being emptie, may hang within halfe a foote of the floore, then ſtande within the Sacke, and receiue the Hoppes, trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding them downe verye harde, and before the Sacke be halfe full, it will reſt vpon the ground, whereby you ſhall be able to preſſe them the har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der togither.</p>
               <p>But the handſommer waye were to make a ſquare hole (as wyde as the Sackes mouth) in the floore of the Lofte, where your Hoppes lye, and to hange downe your Sacke at that hoale, and with a Scuppet or Shoouell to ſhooue down your Hoppes thereinto, and to receyue them as is aforeſayde, when the Sacke is almoſt full, vndoe the Roapes, and wynde thoſe pynnes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout for the harder ſhutting of the Sacke, and faſten them therein.</p>
               <p>If you lyſt, you may ſowe (ouer the mouth of this Sacke) another peece of Sackcloth, wherof you muſt leaue a lyttle vnſowed, vntill you haue
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:3359:32"/> thruſt as many Hoppes as you can betweene the Sacke and the ſame, but in beholding the Hop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſackes ſent from Poppering, you ſhall better vnderſtande and learne the dooings hereof.</p>
               <p>For your owne prouiſion you maye preſerue them in Driefattes, Barrelles, or ſuch lyke veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels, for want of roume to leaue them in, or ſacks to packe them in.</p>
               <p>There is, according to the Prouerbe, much falſhoode in packing, I am vnſkilfull in that Art, if I were otherwiſe, I woulde be loth to teache ſuch doctrine.</p>
               <p>But to auoyde ſuch deceyte, and to make the more perfect and better choyce, it is vſuall and lawfull in moſt places where Hoppes are ſolde, to cut the Sacke that you meane to buye in ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen or eyght places, and to ſearch at eche place whether the Hoppes be of lyke goodneſſe.</p>
               <p>Such places as you ſhall feele with your hand to be ſofter than the reaſt, you ſhoulde ſpeciallye cutte, where perhaps you ſhall fynde Hoppes of another kynde, elder or woorſe than the reſt.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶The reformation of a Garden <hi>of wylde Hoppes.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>TO reforme a Garden where the Hoppes be wylde, the worke is tedious, and none other way remayneth, but to digge ouer the ſame with a Spade, ſo deepe as you maye ſearch out and throw out euery roote and peece of
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:3359:33"/> roote that may be founde in, or neare therevnto, and then to plant according to the order before declared.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶The reformation of a <hi>diſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered Garden.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>TO repayre a ruynous Garden, whiche through ignorauce was diſorderlye ſette, and through ſloth ſuffered to ouerrunne and decay, where neuertheleſſe the Hoppes re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mayne of a good kynde (though ſomewhat em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>payred, as needes they muſt be, by this meanes) the verye beſt waye were to doe as to the wylde Hoppe.</p>
               <p>The ſeconde way is to forget that it is diſorde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red at all, ymagining that all were well, and to ſet your Poales in ſuch order, and ſo farre a ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der as is preſcribed in that tytle, alwayes direc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting them right with a lyne, ſo as a ſtraunger be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holding them, may ſuppoſe that your Garden is kept after the beſt maner, then leade vnto eche Poale two or three ſtalkes which you ſhall fynde neareſt therevnto, and there erecte a hyll which you maye euer after cut and dreſſe according to the rules before declared, and ſo by continuall digging, paring, and diligence, you ſhall at ley<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure bring it to ſome reaſonable perfection.</p>
               <p>If your Garden be verye much matted with rootes, ſo as it be to tedious to dygge, ſet your Poales as you are alredy taught, and bring into
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:3359:33"/> your Garden, and laye neare to euerye ſuch place where you meane to make a hyll, one Coorte loade of good earth, with the which, after your Hoppes are tyed to your Poales, begin to make your hylle, and proceede as in the tytle of Hylles, alwayes cutting downe ſuch Hoppes or weedes as growe betweene the ſayde hylles.</p>
               <p>If your rootes be ſet orderly, and your hilles made accordinglye, and yet left vndreſſed by the ſpace of twoo or three yeares, it will be very hard (I ſay) to diſcerne the ſettes from the other later rootes: neuertheleſſe, if your ground be good, you maye yet reforme the inconuenience thereof, namely, by pulling downe the hill, and cutting a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waye all the rootes contayned therein, euen with the face or vpper part of the earth, ſearching alſo eche ſyde, and digging yet lower, and rounde a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the roote which remayneth, and to take a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waye from the ſame all ſuch rootes as appeare out thereof.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶Needeleſse curioſities vſed by <hi>the vnskilfull.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>TO water your Garden, as to make the rootes growe the better, it were more te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious than needefull, for the hylling ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of ſerueth for that purpoſe, and there is time of growing ſufficient for them betwixt midde A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prill and Auguſt, and yet it neuer hurteth, but rather doth good, if it be before the hyll be made.</p>
               <pb n="52" facs="tcp:3359:34"/>
               <p>To plucke of the leaues, to the ende that the Hoppes may proſper the better, is alſo neede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe, and to no purpoſe, and rather hindereth than helpeth the growth of the Hoppes, for they are hereby depriued of that garment which Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture hath neceſſarilye prouided for them, and clothed them with.</p>
               <p>To flawe the Poales, thereby to prolonge their continuaunce, is more than needeth to be done in this behalfe, for it is too tedious to your ſelfe, and hurtfull to your Hoppe, and little a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uayleth to the purpoſe aforeſayde.</p>
               <p>To burne the nether parte or great ende of your Poales, as ſome doe, to the ende they ſhoulde laſt or endure the longer, is alſo an vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neceſſarie trouble, onelye Willowe Poales you may ſo vſe to keepe them from growing.</p>
               <p>To weede the Hylles with the hande, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as the ſame Weedes ſhall be buryed by the ray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of the hyll.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="epilogue">
            <pb n="53" facs="tcp:3359:34"/>
            <head>The Epilogue.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hus haue I, accordyng to my ſmall ſkyll and experience, according to my friendes deſire, and according to the truth, vtte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red theſe fewe notes concerning the making and mayntenance of an Hoppe garden, that which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mayneth more to be ſayde there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, reſteth in the ſkill of ſkilfuller perſons, and is at this tyme ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther without the compaſſe of my knowledge, or beyonde the reache of my memorie. I doubt not but I haue herein taken vppon me to teach ſome that, which they know bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter than I, and alſo prouoked ſome that néede not, and ſome that care not, to be imployed in theſe matters: howbeit, I vrge nothing, but that which maye bée done without great difficultie, charge, labour, or ſoyle, the matter thereof being in déede to homely and baſe for the prowde and diſdainfull, the exercyſe too tedious and buſie for the ſlothfull and ydle, but the charge too coſtlye for none but Niggards, the cunning too curious for none but fooles, and yet among theſe eſtates (I trowe) there will ſome ſmell out the profitable ſauour of this Herbe, ſome wyll gather the fruite thereof, ſome will make a Sallet therewith (which is good in one reſpect for the bellye, and in another for the Purſe) and when the grace and ſwéete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe hereof is conceyued, ſome will dippe their fingers therein vp to the knuckles, and ſome will be glad to licke the Diſhe, and they that diſdayne to be partakers hereof, commonly prooue to be ſuch, as haue Mountaynes in fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taſie, and beggery in poſſeſſion, I meane that they which haue a Hoppe hyll in deriſion, will ſcant fall out to leaue a Moulehyll in reuerſion. Beſides that, their ſecuritie in this behalfe makes roume for ſtraungers to depryue vs of our commodities, who mayntaine ignoraunce in our
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:3359:35"/> boſomes, and beggerie in our Purſes, whyle we nouriſh diſdayne in our hearts, and ſloth in our handes, and here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by we ſet our ſhame vppon a ſtage for all the worlde to gaze vppon, and make our folly ſo palpable, that Stran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers from beyonde the Seas, (which neither heare nor ſée vs) can grabbe it out, for we can be content vppon our Alebench, to entytle our Countrie to the name of fertili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, and yet depraue the ſame with our péeuiſhneſſe, and ſlaunder it with our ſloth, expounding and excuſing our negligence by our ignoraunce, and couering the one with the others wéedes, the goodneſſe of our grounde ſeruing vs to no other purpoſe, but to manyfeſt our yll huſban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drie, but our abundaunce ſhall not excuſe our vnthanke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe, whyleſt wée abuſe the bleſſinges of God to our owne deſtruction, and oppoſe our ſloth and ignorance a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaynſt hys bountie and goodneſſe, but God forbidde that the prouiſion of the good ſhoulde reſt in the handes of the ſlothfull, from whome let vs depart, and leaue them <hi>fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding their hands togither,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Prouerb. 24.</note> 
               <hi>and ſo ſhall pouertie come vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them.</hi> For, <hi>what felowſhip can there be betweene an holy man and a Dogge,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſi. 13.</note> or betwéene an honeſt man and an vnthrift. Mée thinkes I might aptlye compare ſuch men as haue grounde fitte for this purpoſe, and will not employ it accordingly, to Alehouſe Knightes, partly for the ſmall deuotion which both the one and the other haue vnto Hoppes, but eſpecially for that many of theſe Ale Knightes hauyng good drinke at home of their owne,<note place="margin">Ale to be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended, but not the Ale Knight.</note> can be content to drinke woorſe abroade at an Alehouſe, ſo they may ſit cloſe by it. Let them expounde this compari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon that buye their Hoppes at Poppering, and may haue them at home with more eaſe and leſſe charge, I only ſay that they reſemble &amp; agrée togither though not in good, yet in that which is euil, for I ſée no difference betwixt them, ſauing that vnto the priuate vnthriftyneſſe of the Ale-knights, theſe men adde a publicke deſpyte vnto the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon wealth,<note place="margin">Eccleſ. 14.</note> but <hi>howe can he that is naught himſelfe be
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:3359:35"/> good vnto others.</hi> I for my part know not howe to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade ſuch, nor what they will learne, that refuſe to har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken to their owne profite, for no receyte ſerueth againſt deſpayre, no Counſell preuayleth agaynſt Contempt. Their ground is taught to beare, their Hoppes to grow, their Poales to ſtande, their hands to worke, their ſenſes to perceyue, if they woulde but teach their willes to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent to their owne profite, they ſhoulde haue the gaynes, and I my deſire. If they will not doe ſo much for them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, I pray God that the diligence of the little Emmet which (through their negligence doth much harme to their Hoppe rootes) be not called forth at the laſt daye to witneſſe againſt their ſloth. Now there remayneth no more to be ſayde but a worde or twoo to <hi>Momus,</hi> and his companions, whoſe office reacheth to the reproofe of all things perfect and vnperfect, and therefore my writings miniſtring much cauſe of reprehenſion, muſt néedes be ſubiect to their ſcornes, but I appeale from their mockes to wyſer mens cenſures. For I am perſwaded that I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue rebuke at wyſer mens handes than they are, but their correction will doe me no good, for that it tendeth to the defamation, and not to the reformation of me and my wrytings, I take not vppon me to make a Philoſophye, but a Hoppe garden, and yet I doubt, that bicauſe I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemble not Ariſtotle, this man and his Mates will coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terfeyte <hi>Diogenes,</hi> (that is to ſaye) bicauſe I render not a Perepateticall reaſon for euerye ſillable I write, they will tender a Stoicall frumpe for euery word they reade. Some ſaye that <hi>Momus</hi> for his ſawcyneſſe was torne in thrée péeces. &amp;c. But that little preuayled to allaye the lewdeneſſe of Mockerie, for of one péece were ingendred corrupt and haſtye Iudges, of another, carpcious Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trollers, and of his hinder partes, impudent Scoffers, and thys ſhoulde appeare to be true. For ſome will take vppon them to be Iudges, that (for their integritie) are not méete to be impanelled in a true Iurie, nor for their
<pb facs="tcp:3359:36"/> credite ſcant woorthy to be hangmen to falſe théeues, their iudgementes being corrupt, and alwayes tending to the condemnation of the vnguiltye, their wyſedome ſeruing them to no other ende, but to quarrell with other mens ſimplicities, the ſharpeneſſe of their wyts to nothing but to the maintenaunce of contencion. Some will be Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trollers, that neyther haue authoritie in their perſons, nor wyt in their headdes, reproouing that which neyther they (being fooles) knowe, nor other (béeing wyſe) myſlyke. Finally, ſome are ſo poſſeſſed with the ſpirite of Scur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rillitie, that they cannot gape, but Tauntes appeare in their mouthes, confounding ieaſt and ſobrietie in ſuche ſorte, as though all thinges were but mockerie. I ſaye therefore, that from the hyeſt to the loweſt, from the Iudge to the Hangman, from the top of the Gallowes, to the nethermoſt ſteale of the Ladder, and from Scog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin to Will Summer, there remayneth not one of theſe ſcoffers more fauoured of himſelfe, than abhorred of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, and therefore I woulde wiſhe them, that when their grace, and the Maieſtie of their frumpes fayleth, (that is to ſaye) when men leaue to laugh at their follyes, eyther to ſuppreſſe their ignoraunce with ſuch ſilence, as ſuch as are honeſt, be not gréeued therewith, or to expreſſe their knowledge in ſuch wordes as ſuch as they themſelues are, will not laughe to ſcorne.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
